<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: logging,monitoring | rdotwoolley]]></title>
  <link href="http://rwoolley.github.com/blog/categories/logging-monitoring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rwoolley.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-02T12:56:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rwoolley.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Woolley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Logging as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://rwoolley.github.com/blog/2012/02/01/logging-as-a-service/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-01T20:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rwoolley.github.com/blog/2012/02/01/logging-as-a-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been running into a logging challenge at work of late.  The usual issue.
Lots of logs, in lots of places, retention policies, governance issues,
reporting and (in my humble opinion the most important) support/debugging.  After some searching I
found logg.ly and Papertrail which offered what I wanted as a service.  Very
sweet.  Unfortunately I cannot use them in this implementation so I am pursuing
Graylog2 and logstash (another blogpost on that later). Right now I'm plugging
Papertrail into our demo system to see how it goes and how it fits with our
workflow.  I just wanted to cover off some first impressions with Papertrail.</p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
<li><p>Compatability
We're running RHEL 5.5 (don't judge) so we're using syslog. Luckily there is a
little gem from the Papertrail folks that allows you to pipe your app logs into
their service.  remote_syslog works very well!
Ruby 1.8.7 is our ruby of choice for production systems.  We don't put RVM on
production boxes so our setup is simple in that regard.</p></li>
<li><p>Ease of Use
I love how I can see a window into all the events flying by. This sounds
ridiculous but I can see issues just by watching patterns in the logs. It's
like using the force but it works for me.  Of course you can adjust the
granularity to a specific system.  Search is the next best thing.  90% of my
time spent grovelling in app logs is due to an issue.  Papertrail allows you to
quickly match the user-time-wtf was going on tuple.  Better yet, you can save
any search and run it later. Helpful when you want to see if a fix worked.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>First impressions are great at this point. I think Papertrail has legs.  The
next phase of my thoughts will be around retention and compliance with acts
like HIPAA.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
